[Music]
w
hello and welcome back to the ask abijit
Show episode 227 today I hope everybody
is doing great wherever you are in the
world and before we begin let's see some
who let's see who all is there on the
live chat let me greet some of you I can
see uh super Rex biswajit Lo Shiva Namar
Pria Pavan Kumar Singh ombe ker Tommy
Shelly PR Paul from Kolkata shrikumar
Menan Mr 88 Sally Krishna ragunath from
The Sur from the surinamese
Netherlands uh Kumar aush geopolitical
dub hello Janam Salman Maverick uh t
kalburgi chatan aradya Sam tripati Jin
1045 AJ Raul practics gamer Imran naimi
vior ding dunger Singh Johan hello uh
super Rex dios pitra pushkar Ray rajat
Ragu
Varan uh kg B Tano chakra VAB dangra
utkarsh Zig Jagdish Mali mavin namaskar
Janam chinglin kba ymam from Manipur uh
Mac 4 Sergeant skyin Chan aradya kg t
hardik m abijit m pratik Kish achara
Chri
balb
Vador Sam tripati jardan S yogesh upadhi
sdv B anurag kapalin Sid love science
Arya mahesa prakar Gupta Ria deip
feminist Slayer my cat's birthday Amisha
Mishra hello har on Wheels shayu and
everybody else all right all right let's
get going with the questions I've taken
questions from that you've asked in the
comments I'll take a whole bunch of
those and then maybe some from the live
chat as well so let's go and see what
are the questions that we have today
what questions do we have let's
begin and here we are a whole bunch of
questions about the same thing Trump
Donald Trump and his expansionism CH on
PR Paul the Arian Knight and gorov jat
Mami and a whole lot of other people
have asked this very similar questions
so hopefully these questions will
represent what everybody has asked so
okay chattan thank you for watching for
two years appreciate it very much the
question is why does Trump want
Greenland going as far as to say he will
use military force to take it why is
Trump insisting on taking Canada
Greenland the Panama Canal is it simply
a pressure tactic for trade negot
iations on tariffs or does it make
economic and strategic sense for the US
to govern these regions officially
what's my views on Trump's speeches to
anex Greenland Canada the Panama Canal
and change the name of the Gulf of
Mexico to the Gulf of America is Trump
actually going to do it both France and
Germany have threatened the US with
repercussion repercussions if the US
tries to take Greenland by force do you
think they're allowed to go against the
US what consequences would both
countries face for their actions all
right okay we get it okay everyone's
interested in knowing what's going on is
Trump
serious is he actually planning to Annex
Greenland Canada the Panama Panama can
even Mexico like some some people are
suggesting is he serious can he do it is
the US capable of doing this and will
they face any repercussions if they try
and do that and has Trump said that he
will use military force so first of all
when he when he was asked this question
in a press conference whether he would
be willing uh whether he will
deny the use of military force using
using military force he said no I I will
not rule it out I will not rule it out
so he's not said that he will use
military force he's saying he has said
that he will not rule out the use of
military force to uh to achieve his
objectives okay um so all of that so
what's going on so Trump has made it
very clear that he considers Canada the
51st state of the United States He
taunted Justin tudo while he was still
prime minister by calling him the
governor of the great state of Canada so
he has said that he will Annex
Canada and he said that he will use
economic Force rather than military
force to anex Canada uh when it comes to
Greenland he's very very serious about
it when it comes to the Panama Canal
he's going back into the older chapters
of history and he he has pointed out
that this canal was actually an American
Canal the Americans paid for it and then
it was handed over to the nation of
Panama somewhere in the late 1960s or
thereabouts so the US paid for the thing
it was supposed to be US Territory and
that's what the two governments had
agreed to and then Jimmy Carter I
believe or whoever it was I don't
remember who who it was uh handed over
this canal to Panama after there was a
us uh mediated coup in Panama which
which brought a pro US government to
power and then they handed it over to
can to P Panama so what's Trump trying
to do and is this all possible and where
does it fit in Visa the grand
geopolitical scheme of
things so Trump is serious I'm not sure
whether he wants to actually do all of
this Canada Panama Canal Mexico
Greenland all of that or maybe maybe
he's just after a couple of couple of
things like maybe Greenland and Panama
and maybe he's just putting Canada also
on the platter just to make people you
know worry about Canada and while he's
actually trying to achieve bigger
objectives or maybe he wants Canada as
well at the end of the day the US can do
whatever it wants all of these uh
territories are essentially under Us
control directly or indirectly Denmark
is a small little Nation they have a
very tenuous hold on Greenland the US
can just walk in and there's nothing
Denmark can do about
it um Canada well what can Canada do
about this Canada there's nothing they
can do about it and and apparently there
economy is being subsidized to the tune
of I don't know how many billions of
dollars every year by the Americans so
without the American help they would
collapse so there's that and the US like
Trump said can use economic uh pressure
to induce Canada to merge with the US
when it comes to the Panama Canal the US
can do it of course they can do it
there's nothing Panama can do can do to
prevent the US from taking over the
canal so what will eventually happen
most likely is that the US will give
some token amount of money some token
payment to each country a few billion
dollars here and there maybe they'll
give $10 billion or something I'm just
guessing to Panama for the canal uh
maybe they'll give a few billion dollars
to to Denmark for Greenland and Canada
there's nothing they'll give them
they'll just make them part of their
territory uh so why would you do this
why would Trump want to do this why does
the US need so much more territory isn't
it a headache to govern all this or
maybe the cost benefit
ratio it is it is skewed in in in in the
direction of the benefits rather than
cost so there's more benefit than cost
maybe what could it be like so let's
take a look at the map and that perhaps
will help us understand what's going on
everything in geopolitics boils down to
the map so here's the map of the world
we go to the Western Hemisphere that
here you have the US so he's talking
about Canada which is a gigantic country
larger than in the US he's talking about
the Panama Canal which is over here as
you can see we're zooming into it right
uh that's where the Panama Canal is
located and then there's Greenland which
is this large Frozen apparent Wasteland
now here's the
deal Greenland is rich in natural
resources oil gas coal uh Metals
whatnot and um so that's why it makes a
lot of sense for the US to acquire this
territory from Denmark Denmark has a
very small presence in Greenland they
have very tenuous historical claim to it
it's mostly being a self-governing and
mostly ungoverned territory it's mostly
empty it's all Frozen
glaciers so there is that then Canada is
an extremely large extremely resourcer
territory if the US acquires Canada plus
Greenland they will have a territory
that is larger than that of Russia do
you understand Russia is currently the
largest nation in the world if the
Americans acquire Greenland plus Canada
they will have access to the natural
resources of an entire
continent and the territory they will
own will be larger than that of Russia
and there will be a primary player in
the Arctic Ocean region the Arctic
Circle region which because of climate
change because of global warming is
slowly thawing up and there's a lot of
resources to be found under the ocean
and in this overall region the Arctic
Ocean region and right now Russia is the
major player here and Canada well Canada
is hardly a player but it it controls a
lot of Arctic territory because it owns
the territory so with the us acquiring
Canada and Greenland they will become
probably a more major player than Russia
they will they'll maybe bump Russia to
number two when it comes to the Arctic
great game so that is the reason why the
Americans are going for Canada and
Greenland and they will most likely
acquire these two territories within a
few years before Trump deits office and
when it comes to Panama the Panama Canal
well it's an extraordinarily important
geopolitical geographical choke point in
in uh in the world it's one of the major
choke points like the like the Su Canal
the the malaka strait and and much more
the Baba Al mandb straight the straet of
Hormuz and the Panama Canal so a very
very large portion of uh of Maritime
traffic passes through the Panama Canal
and whoever controls it controls
essentially global trade to a very large
extent so it makes sense for the
Americans to control this and not leave
it to Panama which kind of is a US proxy
but why not control it ourselves
entirely directly without the need for
inter for you know going through a third
party so the
Americans manufactured the canal they
they they constructed the canal they
paid for the whole thing and then they
gave it to Panama so now it makes sense
for them to take it back so once again
if the Americans decide to do this it'll
it can happen
tomorrow so a lot of geopolitical change
is coming up I believe Trump is very
serious when he says he wants to do this
and it makes a lot of sense for the US
in this very rapidly changing
geopolitical climate to acquire these
territories and take Direct Control and
ownership of these territories without
having to go through through
intermediaries like the Canadian Prime
Minister the Danish government whatever
they'll just walk in and take over so it
will need some reorganization of the US
I mean Canada has multiple States you
know Alberta saskachewan British
Colombia Manitoba Ontario Quebec new
fundland and leor in the Northwest
Territories Yukon nut and so on so will
each of these territories of Canada
provin Canadian provinces become a US
state or will Canada o overall become a
US possession the way Puerto Rico is so
all that needs to be seen it remains to
be seen but uh I think it's a matter of
time before the Americans take over
Canada and Greenland I'll be surprised
if they don't take Canada uh Greenland
is
essentially just you just need a
signature on on on paper from Trump for
that to happen and so with Panama Canada
may be a little more delicate operation
but it too from my perspective will
happen so so that's how I see this
happening now let's coming let's come
back to the questions um does it make uh
economic and strategic sense for the US
to govern these regions officially yes
it does make a lot of sense for them to
govern these regions directly it's some
of it could be a pressure tactic but
what's the point of threatening to take
over Canada I mean who are you
pressurizing by doing that you're not
really pressurizing
anybody uh so I think it could happen
within the next four years and that's
going to be very
interesting it'll totally uh recalibrate
reconfigure the geopolitical chess
board okay abial Singh says with
musk excuse
me obal Singh says with Trump and musk
threatening European politicians with
scandals in the Elation of Canada and
Greenland do you think NATO will
disintegrate I think NATO will not
disintegrate to the contrary NATO will
become more centralized and stronger I
think that's what will most likely
happen we know that Elon Musk is right
now actively participating in the uh
internal politics of multiple Nations
including the UK and and uh Germany and
Trump is obviously threatening he he is
he has announced that he plans to Annex
various other nations like Greenland and
Canada Etc so so um so Greenland is part
of Denmark Canada is is a Sovereign
Nation well technically technically it
is okay um so if the US annexes these
nations and the the US interferes medals
in the internal politics of Germany UK
Etc what could happen will it cause NATO
to disintegrate let's see see UK is a US
what's the V word it's a US V okay uh it
exists at the pleasure of the US it it
acts as an extension of the US economy
and US foreign policy the UK the UK is
not really a Sovereign Nation okay it's
an extension of the US it's a vasal a
feudatory of the US and when it comes to
Germany it's a nation that's under
permanent us occupation military
occupation since 1945 take a look at how
many permanent US military bases exist
on German soil take a look at who wrote
the German Constitution and so on you
will see that Germany is hardly a
Sovereign Nation it's uh a US possession
so the US can do whatever it wishes with
Germany and uh they will install uh a
chancellor of their choice it's always a
chancellor of the US's choice in Germany
so no big deal whether it's the UK
whether whether it's Germany there's
nothing these nations can do about what
the US does to them there's nothing they
can do to uh remove themselves from NATO
it will not be allowed to happen so I
think NATO is going to become a more
monolithic block going forward when it
comes to multilateral organization the
most powerful Nation within that
organization is always the top dog and
that's a nation that calls all the shots
with NATO it's always been that way and
now it's going to be even more that way
so I don't see NATO disintegrating I see
NATO NATO becoming even more monolithic
going forward that's how I see it
happening okay nand kizor says Andrew
Tate has started his own party and is
running for the next UK election what
are your thoughts on this and is Elon
Musk behind this because he was going
all out on the U UK government the past
two months and also he urged for a
regime
change there's multiple moving moving
Parts in this so I remember about a year
or so ago somebody asked me on a live
chat on a previous episode of this show
what are your views on Andrew Tate and I
was like who's Andrew Tate I've never
heard of him and then after then that
sub subsequently I took a look at who
this guy is and I now I know what he
means what what what he is who he is
what what he represents and so on so
forth uh the manosphere and whatnot
right uh
so now Andrew Tate has thrown his hat
into the ring in UK politics I think
he's a UK citizen his father is American
but I think he's he and his brother are
UK citizens British citizens so he's
thrown his hat into the ring he has
launched a new political party called
brv bruv there's a Twitter account
associated with that um and he says he's
100% serious and he says he has the
money to fund his own campaigns and all
that so uh what does it mean I don't
think it's going to really fundamentally
change UK politics I'm not sure if he
will be I know I'm not sure if he will
be taken seriously at this point you
have to really you know pay your dues
before you are taken seriously in
politics uh you come out of nowhere and
throw your hat in the ring people won't
take you seriously but if you persevere
over three or four over two or three or
four electoral Cycles then it shows
people that you are serious just saying
you're serious is not
enough so you to persist you to
persevere you to pay your dues you to
fight in the trenches and so on so once
he does that over a few years he may be
taken seriously he may at this point in
time it's to for that and and Elon Musk
has been criticizing lambasting
excoriating Kier starmer and his track
record with very good reason uh the UK
is probably the world's rape Capital
right uh and Elon Musk has been
highlighting this I mean the rham
grooming Scandal and all that that's
been going on for 20 plus years it's
been known for a very long time everyone
knew about this but they all kept it
quiet they all brushed it under the
carpet and there was a time when this
guy K starmer the current prime minister
of the UK was the head of the crown
police or whatever it's called and he
was in charge of dealing with this and
he ensured that no action is taken
against the pakistanis who were doing
this all across the country and I don't
understand what sort of nation the UK is
they get all all riled up when there's a
negative result in a football match they
go on a rampage whism and all but when
this is being done to their daughters
they're just quiet like sheep I don't
know what kind of nation it is I think a
bunch of losers the UK they should be
ashamed of themselves oh good God so
that's what Elon Musk has been talking
about and that's what I think Andrew
Tate also has
referenced um yeah so um so I don't
think it's going to really affect uh the
results of of future elections
immediately Andrew Tate's entry into UK
politics but Elon Musk has been calling
for a regime change for sure so most
like within sometime within a few months
maybe within a few weeks K starmer will
most likely resign sooner or later I'm
saying this right now I'm making a
prediction kir starmer will find his
situation increasingly untenable as
prime minister he will soon resign maybe
in a few weeks maybe in a few months and
then a new US puppet will be brought to
power will be installed on the seat of
the UK prime minister and at the end of
the day it will make no difference
whatsoever maybe the grooming gangs some
of you know there there may be some sort
of clamp down on it to some extent I'm
not sure you can give justice to all the
girls who have been you know
victimized uh generations of girls who
have been victimized I don't think
they'll be able to bring the Pakistani
terrorists or whatever you know the
monsters to justice but yeah that's the
kind of nation the UK has become
pathetic they they should be ashamed of
themselves they should be ashamed to
show their face in public the people of
the
UK absolute bunch of pathetic cowards
that's what they
are um yeah so these are my thoughts on
this prai Paul says China Shi Jin has
recently acknowledged external
uncertainties in his new year's speech
how do you see China's Behavior
unfolding this year is the economic and
political bubble under she becoming too
large to sustain additionally with
reports of sudden virus outbreaks in
China do you think these could be
deliberate
disruptions how should India prepare and
respond proactively to avoid risks and
ensure stability so Shi Jinping has
definitely certainly indeed acknowledged
external uncertainties in his new year's
speech and well every nation faces
external uncertainties there's always an
environment environment outside of a
Nation an environment you cannot
directly
control that affects
what happens to you to your economy to
your nation to your exports Imports and
so on so forth international relations
all of that there's always external
uncertainties but what Xi Jinping is
referring to is the reelection of Donald
Trump and we know that Donald Trump is a
is a hawk when it comes to the US
relationship with China he is the
president who started the US trade war
against China by by increasing the
tariffs and trade trade barriers and all
that and he's going to once he is back
in the white house he's going to push
forward on that he is right now like an
elephant stomping around the room right
he's he is planning to Annex Nations
entire
nations um and that's going to totally
upend the geopolitical chessboard the
geopolitical uh balance of power the
geopolitical equations the set of
equations and so on and that's going to
be very concerning for
China uh when it comes to Biden he
himself has carried forward the trade
war that Trump launched and it's really
affected China very badly uh there's
trade and tariff barriers all over the
place for China China is the world's
largest manufacturer but now with so
many trade and tariff barriers it's not
uh it doesn't make economic sense for
Nations to
import uh goods from China because you
know because of the trade and tariff
barriers which makes the goods more
expensive so it makes sense to Source
them locally or from other places right
and that's what the West is doing to
China the West obviously follows the
lead of the US so that's the deal so
China is facing a lot of pressure
increasing pressure it's feeling the
pinch um so that's the situation with
China so that's the external
uncertainties that sh that President Shi
Jinping was referring to so how do I see
China's Behavior unfolding this year
they will continue the pressure on
Taiwan there's no doubt about that and
they will continue whatever uh
activities they do the in the Border
regions including the recently renamed a
coule they recently created new counties
in Ain to kind of RI India to a bit yeah
uh so those provocative activities will
continue the pressure on Taiwan will
continue maybe there'll be something
with Japan the sen Kaku diu islands that
those or flights the South China Sea uh
issue will continue so they won't uh
they won't pull down on any of that but
when it comes to the overall larger
India China relationship they seem to be
you know showing signs of wanting better
relations well we have to trust but
verify or rather verify and then think
about trusting when it comes to China
because of the past 70 years of History
starting from the 1950s in which we have
you know the Chinese have been extremely
aggressive and uh they have wanted to
break up India they have they have
generals and writers who have written
about the need to balkanize India
they've supported anti-india separatist
activities in India's Far East in
nagaland and other places and you know
the whole history there's been War 1962
1987 with China lost 1967 the China lost
and so on so there's this whole baggage
of history that we have and then there's
the enormous undemarcated border which
obviously is the source of a lot of
tension between India and China so uh
all of that is there but the Chinese are
showing signs of wanting things to
become more normal more normalization
with India maybe the thought maybe aimo
or whatever so we have to be very
cautious when it comes to this we would
take it one step at a time very slowly
proceed forward and at the end of the
day the resolution to the to the entire
issue is the demarcation of the Border
but that's very far away until that's
not done things could blow up any time
essentially so there's been some
pullback from from both sides on the
border on the Lac line of actual control
but we're going to have to be very
cautious when it comes to our
relationship with China maybe and and
it's very clear that because of the
tremendous pressure they facing from the
US that's why they want a better
relationship with India because if India
also decides that let's give up and die
and become a US Bal then it's it's it's
very bad news for
China right so that's that's why the
Chinese seem to want a better
relationship with India but we we're
going to have to be very cautious about
that uh the sudden virus out breaks
reports of that in China well we have to
keep an eye on that I hope there's
nothing serious I I I don't think
anybody in the world wants a repeat of
what happened a few years ago we don't
want any of that again I mean that was
devastating for the world it was
devastating for entire economies for
individuals for families we don't want
that again so I hope the Chinese
government can control any potential
virus outbreak any future virus outbreak
I don't know if these could be
deliberate disruptions can't speculate
but India is going to have to be very
cautious when it comes to China we
should if the Chinese are sincere in
wanting better relations we should very
much welcome that uh we have no
civilizational or cultural or religious
issu with China it's just a border thing
uh so we GNA we should welcome Chinese
uh intentions of they are sincere and uh
we should take it step by step one step
at a time and I think that that process
is kind of happening so it's by doing
this confidence building measures and
People to People connections and blah
blah blah all that stuff that we could
build more trust and hopefully ensure
stability going forward in the long
run okay Vikram Ador and geopolitical
dubet I recently read an article
confirming Indonesia's entry in into
bricks while we see many nations apply
for the bricks membership I wonder how
long will the block survive and be
relevant considering there's no
consensus between the three top three
nations India Russia and China with
respect to issues like dollarization and
so on China wants to use an alternative
bricks currency to further its National
interest and grow its economy which can
be a threat for India if China grows
stronger isn't it a threat for Russia as
well how do how do you see the future of
this block in the coming decades and can
r i Russia India China this trilateral
block if formed officially can r i
handle the so superpower which is the US
is the US that power is the US powerful
enough to counter the r i together is
the US immune to any threat okay let's
first talk about bricks then we'll talk
about r r but the two questions are
definitely correlated so Indonesia has
apparently entered into bricks I haven't
seen the news but let's say it's true
okay or or why don't we just Google it
so let's let's
Google let's Google
it um
okay one
second let us Google
it Indonesia breaks Indonesia defense BR
okay it has officially become the first
Southeast Asian okay all right so it's
clear that Indonesia has indeed join
bricks very good I'm I'm happy to hear
this so a lot of Nations want to join
bricks you right and you're also right
in asking how long could this block
survive and be relevant because there's
no significant consensus between the top
three nations Russia India
China
um on various matters so now we have to
understand why did bricks why was this
grouping formed in the first
place it was created as an economic
grouping see the West has been dominant
the past Century past five centuries and
now there are the older economies the
older civilizations are rising again
India and China essentially Russia is
also an Eastern civilization not
Western uh so it's it's kind of the the
East coming together in some some sort
of way to try and find some way to
cooperate economically there a bricks
Bank bricks Development Bank and so on
there's various
uh various organs or organizations that
have been set up to uh to uh to to bring
to take this cooperation forward to act
as vehicles that takes this that take
this cooperation forward so bricks is
kind of it is definitely not a strategic
Alliance it's not a military Alliance
it's not even an alliance it's just a
coalition of of Nations and it's an
economic Coalition of Nations and you
could say sort of that it emerged as a
response to the Western hegemony of the
world for five
centuries in real reaction to the
Western heery that's that's the context
and in reaction to India China Russia
again reemerging as Powers so when it
comes to economics China is the biggest
economy of the three r i of of the
bricks economies uh India is the second
largest of the bricks economies and
Russia is probably third largest if you
cut out lots of extraneous factors and
look at just the bare bones definition
of GDP then Russia could be in the top
three um
there you have that
right so there there are issues of
course like you say between India and
China between China and Russia and so on
and obviously the Chinese Every Nation
wants look Every Nation priori
prioritizes its own self-interest when
you are in bricks you want to extract
some value out of bricks for your own
self-interest and every nation sees
bricks in this way uh so it can only
work when when there's Synergy between
the top three Nation s so how long could
bricks last I think bricks will last
significantly long because there is a
common adversary or threat when it comes
to economics and other
matters Vis A with respect from the
perspective of the East so when it comes
to Russia India China we have a common
adversary of sorts well from the Indian
perspective you could not really say
that the US is an adversary but their
actions are anything but friendly and
their actions have been anything but
friendly the past three or four years
the US they've used all kinds of
pressure tactics against
India um they've tried to to tarish
India's image in so many different ways
they've tried to arm twist India in so
many ways they're currently armed
testing India when it comes to delivery
of fighter jet engines and so many other
things so the relationship isn't good
anymore between India and the US and
it's because India's U status is a
growing economy and the US doesn't want
India to end up becoming the next China
in the next 20 30 years so that's why
they're trying to clamp down from right
from right now itself
itself so that's why you could say that
the US is behaving like an adversary to
India so from that perspective India
China Russia have kind of common ground
to work to work towards right uh so as
long as the US is a hegeman a global
hegeman a superpower a very powerful
Nation bricks will continue to exist
unlike unless there's a war very
unlikely war between India and China or
China and Russia which is extremely
unlikely I mean how stupid it would be
to for for India and China to go to war
or China and Russia to go to war India
and Russia there's no chance of a war no
chance in hell of a war but China India
and China Russia are the historical flas
points but it makes sense for these
countries to work together so I I see
bricks remaining relevant for a few
decades at least for a few decades at
least a decade 100% a decade and and
it's it's really attractive the bricks
economy cumulative economy is greater
than the the G7 economies is now which
is why nations are really interested in
joining that's why Indonesia wants to
join and so many other nations want to
join they are all queuing up so makes
sense so I think bricks will remain
relevant for a few decades uh now about
Ric if R I actually becomes a military
Coalition let's say okay well that
that's like uh hell freezing over or the
sun rising in the East but let's say R
becomes a military Coalition an actual
military Alliance then canot handle the
soul superpower you understand if you
want to become a military Alliance you
have to work out all kinds of extremely
complicated and and U
confounding
details if we are a military Alliance do
we pull our Armed Forces together who
controls the Armed Forces who commands
the Armed Forces where does the command
center
lie lot of details that are extremely
prickly but let's say it happens okay so
we what that means is that you simply
take the hard power score of each of the
three nations and add it together into a
single hard power score so what Russia
is about what is it let's say it's 50
China is 17 and India is
4.9 so 60 + 17 is 77 plus 4.9 is 81 81
82 and the US is about 94 so that makes
it very similar to the US you know the
hard power of R Plus versus us it's
still less than the us but it is not far
away so it's 84 versus 82 versus 94 just
a difference of 12 points so that would
make it a significant Challenger to the
US but it would need to have a single uh
Power Center you can't have
decentralized power centers otherwise if
if if you have that then it doesn't work
properly you don't have the agility and
the speed of decision making that you
would want you know you would have to do
decision Decisions by consensus which
never works
uh so if RC is formed then it could
really genuinely counterbalance the
US uh the US is still going to be more
powerful than RC put together but uh it
will be a genuine uh means of
counterbalance in the US and it would
genuinely split the world essentially in
half uh so yeah r i if it comes together
very unlikely extremely unlikely but if
it happens then it could
genuinely counterbalance the US from a
position of slight inferiority
is the US immune to any threat no nation
is immune to any threat no superpower is
immune to
threats right even the Roman Empire
wasn't immune to threats even the Maia
Empire wasn't immune to threats no no
geopolitical entity is immune entirely
to
threats PR Paul says if is China's
decision to Stage the ramay and promote
bat naum among children is shared by
yujing spokesperson of the Chinese
Embassy in India and the Chinese
ambassador to India extending warm
greetings on world Hindi day 2025 with a
video on X are all these things signs of
genuine long-term cultural alignment or
is this a calculated strategic move
considering China's demographic and
financial
challenges look culturally India and
China have been aligned for a very long
time 200 years
plus um the Chinese Communist party took
Chinese culture in a very different
Direction they tried to kind of Smash
out Stamp Out old culture old Chinese
culture but of late they have realized
the Folly of doing so and now they are
trying to use China's culture as
something that um augments China's power
soft power worldwide and China's uh
image and all that but when it comes to
the Chinese Communist Party culture is a
means to an end it's not the end
itself the Chinese Communist party's
overall objective is domination its
expansion of their power essentially
China becomes the center of Heaven the
Middle Kingdom right uh that's being
their original goal right now it they
understand it's very very difficult to
make it happen anytime soon so right now
they have toned down the rhetoric and
all that but overall that's always being
the Chinese Communist party's
agenda now India and China culturally we
align there's no issue with our culture
there's no cultural issues that we have
V China like like we have with the
Western world or the or any other part
of the world our cultures are very
compatible India and China Indian
culture is not compatible with the with
abrahamic culture which is
supremacist and and expansionist and
destructive but uh India and China's
cultures are very compatible uh so there
is definitely cultural alignment there's
no question about it and you could the
Chinese have no issue with Indian
culture and they will definitely see
this as LW hanging fruit so saying some
nice things about India on world Hindi
day maybe you know um having some
programs on world yoga day Chinese
people doing yoga thousands of them
looks very nice Indians very easy to
make Indians happy uh stage the you know
stage the ramayan you know have plays of
the
ramayan you know conducted in China
promote bat naam among children it
doesn't harm China any any any way at
all by doing these things it is not a
threat to Chinese civilization or
culture doing any of this but they will
definitely clamp down on Christianity in
Islam in China but they are okay with
Hinduism because we are compatible
cultures so uh that is fine so the
Chinese are doing that and by doing
these things the Chinese are signaling
to India that we desire better
relations that's what they are signaling
to India how sincere are they is to be
seen but one can be optimistic and say
that maybe the Chinese are sincere so
let's take it one one step at a time
let's meet and see what they they seek
and see what we seek and let's see
what's common in between these two
things and let's work together towards
that and we'll see one step at a time
how sincere they are and they can also
see how sincere we are and that's how
you go forward in diplomacy and in
international
relations so it's definitely something
we can do is this a calculated strategic
move considering China's various
challenges definitely it is that as well
it is as well right right now the whole
world's economy is shutting down CL it's
shutting its doors to Chinese Imports by
putting up these trade and tariff
barriers so where does China export all
of its goods it is the world's largest
manufacturing capability capacity but
where does it export everything without
the export the Chinese economy dies so
by by uh bettering relations with India
they are hoping that they can get access
to the Indian economy and then India and
China trade can really go up and that's
what they seek so they they you know the
past few years the Indian economy has
completely shut down to the Chinese
there's still trade going on I mean
India is exporting raw materials and and
importing Chinese finished products
because India has failed in becoming at
becoming manufacturing power past 10
years I don't know what happened but
it's not happened so there's this big
trade imbalance and if uh the Chinese
get access to the Indian market the
trade imbalance could get
worse but yeah that that is the deal so
it's definitely related linked to the
Chinese to the challenges the Chinese
are facing the geopolitical demographic
Financial economic challenges the
Chinese are facing and for that they
need to have better relations with India
it makes sense from a strategic
perspective so that's why they're doing
all this and it's okay we know why
they're doing it but but if it leads to
better relations it's good for us as
well so we should take it one step time
very cautiously but we can be
optimistic danush and vickram
geopolitical the dry variant of the
calary engine for the gatak um aircraft
has been approved for testing and
reports are saying that the engine could
be in production by 2026 given this news
is there is there a good chance that we
may be able to succeed with the calary
programs so that we don't have to depend
on buying the technology from other
nations Dro has announced the Cav engine
has been cleared for infl flight testing
marking a significant development in so
on so forth the testing location will be
the gromov flight Research Institute
located near Moscow Russia how big of a
development is this it's a good
development it's a positive development
please understand that this is not the
full version of of the cavar engine this
is the dry variant of the car engine
what is the difference between a dry
variant and a vet variant the dry
variant of an engine is a is an engine
that doesn't have afterburners
and the vet variant of an engine is an
is a version of the engine that can
ignite afterburners that give a
significant short-term boost to the to
the fighter plane so afterburners are
when you when a plane is taking off okay
let's just Google it instead of
describing it uh
theoretically let us Google
it so after burners
After Burner so this is what
afterburners look like when a plane is
taking off it it puts on this big jet
long
jet over here you can see it and it it
and you can see shock diamonds or Mark
diamonds in the afterburner uh images
right so generally when a plane is
flying you will not see this exhaust
this this exhaust on fire behind it so
this is used only when you're taking off
or when you want to suddenly acquire a
very rapid burst of speed in in a very
short time that's when you use the After
Burner and to when you use the After
Burner it it consumes a lot of fuel a
lot more of fuel than it otherwise would
consume so it's only for takeoffs and
and dog fighting and all that that you
use after burners and that's something
that you need in fight a plane without
after burners you are like kind of
handicapped
uh so the dry version of the Cav engine
doesn't have After Burner
capability so it's not the the final
version of the engine that you want to
use in in your fighter planes it's it's
kind of a reduced version but anyway
it's it's it's good progress it's going
to be used for the gatak aircraft which
is a bat-shaped aircraft it's a stealth
aircraft unmanned aircraft that India is
developing uh so it's a good it's it's
it's a good step it's good progress my
question is why don't we have testing
facilities in India are we a nation that
lacks money or resources why is the
government of India why have they been
sleeping on this so long why don't we
have our own flight testing facilities
engine testing facilities you need a
test bed for that a test bed is is Def
is essentially an aircraft with
generally you have a four engine
aircraft like 747 or one of the very
military transport planes huge ones with
four engines and one of those four
engines is taken out and it's replaced
by the engine you want to test so even
of the engine malfunctions you still
have three functioning engines and the
plane will survive no matter what
happens in the test so that's a test bed
why doesn't India have a single test bed
why hasn't the government of India
invested in a single test bed why don't
we have flight testing uh capabilities
why do we have to send an engine to
Russia for this this tells you why why
India doesn't do well in these matters
we are simply not serious about these
things we're going to Outsource
everything to
others um yeah so that's that's a sad
State of Affairs that we have in India
and people say that you are very
negative well these are fact
right uh yeah so so that's the deal so
um it's it's an incremental development
it's not going to be powerful enough
this engine for the the fighter plane or
future fighter planes amca or whatever
for for that to happen you would need a
vet variant of the car engine with full
After Burner
capabilities but uh I'm glad the dry dry
variant is being tested and hopefully it
does well and by 26 we can use it in our
unmanned aircraft like the gatak and so
on so it's incremental progress but we
really really need to have our own
full-fledged jet engine for fighter
planes no matter what it takes no matter
what it
costs TR Paul says with the if Chief
Indian Air Force Chief highlighting
frustration over the sluggish pace of
Tes production staying Tech saying that
stating that Tech delayed is Tech denied
and increased militarization by China
and Pakistan posing serious security
concerns how can India strike a balance
between speeding up indigenous defense
projects and addressing immediate border
challenges look when it comes to border
challenges you put the right amount the
requisite amount of of personnel and
materials on the border you deploy that
properly you need to have border
infrastructure like roads and Railways
and all which we are doing I am very
pleased with the way the government has
gone about doing that excellent job uh
the Border roads organization has been
working day and night no matter what the
climate is like no no matter whether
it's raining or snowing or whatever
they've been working day and night so
great progress on this front India has
really uh caught up with the Chinese
infrastructure on various portions of
the India India Tibet border so that's
that's great work you got to hand it to
the government great job on that so we
need to leverage that and place the
right amount of of men and material on
the border to deal with the the Border
challenges but when it comes to the
technological challenges and
capabilities the Chinese now have two
fifth generation fighter planes and they
could transfer some of these or sell
some of these to Pakistan which which
will give us a tremendous headache right
from from two from two flanks a two
front
headache uh now the Chinese are making
noises that they want to be friends with
India again well I'm glad they're doing
it but we still cannot discount the fact
that they are a very powerful nation and
we have this whole history of hostility
so India needs to have something to
counter all that and for that we need to
produce to to take these programs
forward the amca program and whatever
else the advanced medium combat aircraft
the twin engine jet deck based fighter
te dbf and so on so for whatever is
there we need to
really step up uh the the the the gas on
these things uh now when it comes to the
thees fighter planes the the if Chief
said that orders that were placed in
2010 still haven't been delivered which
is shocking so you know what should be
done we can sit here and cry and
criticize and point fingers but what
should be done drdo needs to be overh
hold Dro is an extremely
outdated bureaucratic
organization
5,000 scientists and engineers and 30 25
to 30,000 non-scientific
Personnel why do you need 25 to 30,000
non science Personnel in Dro fire them
all lay them off transfer them somewhere
else how much imagine how much salary
they are they drawing every every
month much of the scientific budget is
going towards paying these people's
salaries we need to cut down on all this
nonsense and drdo I mean they've done
lot of good work not great work but good
work but they can do more they can do
better they have a similar they have a
similar budget as
DARPA DARPA has just twice the budget as
drdo not 10 times not 50 times not 100
times just twice the budget as Dro and
see what what the American DARPA can do
the most spectacular technological
achievements and the DARPA and when it
comes to DARPA you know how many people
they have on their payroll at any given
point in time 150 scientists or
Engineers that's it we have 5,000
scientists or engineers in Dro and 25 to
30,000 non-scientific Personnel I don't
know what those people are doing so we
need to cut down all all this nonsense
the government knows this I first said
this in 2019 or something in Cherry
right it's been what 6 years 5
years we need to cut down on all this
really we need to we need to make these
organizations lean and mean and
everything should be based on
performance if you don't perform you
should be fired right The Dru has these
uh tages production lines so apparently
we can produce 16 Tes fighters in a year
why only 16 why don't why not make two
or three more production lines and R up
the production to at least 32 or maybe
50 per year why not do that don't we
have the money to set up more production
lines don't we have 1.54 billion people
in India who are thirsting for jobs and
who will work on the production lines
and they all qualified they all have the
degrees why not do this what is
preventing us from doing it am I
criticizing the government too much am I
being unjust in my
criticism so all this can be done
and at the end of the day the the the
Cav engine has to work or just buy a jet
engine I don't care how much they charge
for it get a full transfer of Technology
what's 5 billion 10 billion what is it
it's nothing for India cut down on your
larly beh yoga or what this yoga or that
yoga cut down on all these things free
bees free apartments for people I don't
know what the hell slum dwellers why do
we even need slums send them back to the
village and have
set up the right environment in all
Villages for people to get employment
there so there are so many issues there
are clear-cut solutions to the issues
but who's going to implement
them vickram geopolitical says why
didn't India buy the fifth generation
sukko 57 from Russia instead of going
for the 4.5 generation Rafal Russia is a
friend of ours we could and they could
have agreed of course they'll agree
today if we want they'll agree today if
we want so India and Russia were working
on the fifth generation fighter aircraft
the fgfa project which was an aircraft
that's a derivative of the suko 57 so
India and Russia this this project
started I don't know maybe around 2010
maybe give or take a few years but
roughly 2010 don't quote me on that look
it up on Wikipedia or wherever so around
2010 this joint venture starts the fgfa
project which is going to be a new
aircraft B based on the soo
57 and India wants it to be a twin twin
fighter sorry a twin pilot aircraft the
so 57 has one Pilot We want a two-pilot
aircraft and we want some some changes
some some improvements to the s57 fight
a plane some 50 plus improvements India
wanted more stealth capabilities more
this more that this that this that this
that and this was supposed to be a joint
venture means half the work is done by
Russia or half and half the work is done
by India and at the end of the day the
be a full technology transfer to India
and India will pay a significant amount
of money for that and over
time uh India found that uh it was not
getting what it it was paying for India
was footing much of the bill but India
was not getting the technology transfer
most of the critical design Etc work was
being done by in Russia and they were
reluctant to to hand over the the the
blueprints and the technology and all
that and then around 2017 2018 the
Russians asked for what $9 billion or
something so there said you want the
technology is going to cost some more I
would say India should have handed over
the $9 billion and taken the full
technology transfer but India
discontinued the project maybe there
there have been good reasons for it okay
we I can only tell you what is available
in the public domain I'm sure there's a
lot that's classified and that we not
know about so maybe some things happened
that were not right for us maybe maybe
not I don't know so we withdrew from the
project after sinking a lot of money
into the project
and the Russi Russians have said that
India is welcome to uh restart the
project at any time India said that we
will think about it after the so 57 is
actually deployed so now it's
deployed so is India thinking about it
or not I don't know I I would say that
look the sukko
57 is a fifth generation fighter
plane uh I'm sure it's not as stealthy
as the world's stealthiest aircraft like
we wanted but I'm sure it's stealthier
than the
and it has capabilities that the Rafal
doesn't have as a 4.5 generation fital
plane so was it a good decision to
abandon the joint project with the
Russians we wanted a super sukko 57 we
wanted a suko 57 with like 57 or
something 54 50 plus improvements on the
sukko 57 two pilots instead of one uh
avionic same but uh more stealth
features the all kinds of stuff okay all
kinds of extra improvements
so I would say that even if we get zero
improvements but we get the technology
transfer of the Suk 57 as it is today
and we have to pay $9 billion for it we
should do
it we should do
it so I don't get what the Armed Forces
brass want they want the best of off
everything at the end of the day you
have what Mig
21s and
jaguars and suco
30s and some rafales a handful small
handful like salt sprinkling of rafales
why not have 200 300 Su 57s that you can
build on your own because you have the
technology why not do that pay the money
right I don't know what goes on what
considerations are there what
calculations are there
uh maybe the Russians
possibly were not willing to give the
full technology even after paying $9
million that's also a possibility so it
it would be unfair to criticize the
government entirely without knowing the
full details and the full details are
obviously classified so we don't know
but I would say that compared to the
Rafal see the Rafal is a great aircraft
but the Suka 57 at least on paper from
what I see is a much better aircraft
it's a fifth generation fighter plane it
would make sense for us to have a few
hundred of those that would seriously
you know ease the pressure on India when
it comes to the Chinese developments and
the in the POS potential sale of Chinese
fifth generation fighter planes to
Pakistan it would be great for India to
have uh 200 or 300 sukko 57s with
production lines in India with the full
technology transfer in India whatever it
costs I don't care it's a matter of
National Security in the meanwhile we
can continue building uh you know
developing the fifth generation fighter
plane the amca the the TBF and all that
we can continue work on those
things but we should at least get one
fifth generation fighter plane
now uh so yeah that's where we
are Vikram geopolitical says how will
India Canada relations evolve after
Justin Trudeau stepped down as the prime
minister of Canada yes Miss Justin
Trudeau has stepped down as the prime
minister of Canada uh I think he decided
that I have done enough damage to the
world and now I will step back step down
step down so now that he's gone and
somebody new will
eventually be placed in power as the
prime minister of Canada how will India
Canada relations
evolve
okay here's the deal when it comes to
India Canada
relations Canada
Harbors a very
rabid very
hostile khalistan
population these are Canadian citizens
who espouse the
fictitious La La Land dream of khalistan
creating khalistan out of Indian
Territory they don't want to create
khalistan out of Pakistani territory
Pakistani occupied Punjab they don't
want that they want it to be cared out
of Indian
Punjab these are anti-india elements
they call for the assassination of
Indian diplomats Prime Ministers they
celebrate the assassination of prime
minister IND Gandhi's um her
assassination they are the ones who blew
up an entire aircraft once the Canadian
government
just you know they push that
investigation under the carpet so as
long as this situation continues and as
long as these khalistani terrorists keep
getting uh political mileage and support
from all the PO Canadian political
parties India Canada relations will
never go back on track and the onus for
this lies on Canada not on India we
don't Harbor those khalistanis the
Canadians are harboring the
khalistanis and various assorted
anti-india
elements so as long as Canada does this
India Canada relations cannot go back on
track it's as simple as that whether
it's just in trudo who's prime minister
or or Pierre po who's who's prime
minister or whoever else is prime
minister it doesn't matter as long as
their political system continues to to
uh support the
khalistanis and and make them an
integral part of their politics things
won't work so I don't see any
Improvement any significant Improvement
in India Canada relations anytime
soon Vikram Ador says As Trump returns
to power can we see imch Corridor resume
sometime this year because Trump has
threatened Hamas to return all the
hostages otherwise they'll be hell
Unleashed yes as we know he has good
ties with Israel and he was pretty tough
on Iraq in his last term and will back
Israel till it fulfills its objectives
and also in the IMC there are other
allies like Jordan Saudi Arabia and the
UA chances are War might end this year
what are your views about this good
question very interesting question let's
go to the map to understand the
situation with the imech so let's go to
the
map so what is this imech the imch is
the India middle east Europe Corridor
it's a trade and transportation Corridor
it will start one of its terminals will
be the entire west coast of India I
think Mumbai is one of the major ports
and from Mumbai you go to the UAE there
will be a port somewhere in the northern
part of the UAE okay which is going to
be one of the major points in the imch
from the UA the the corridor goes on VI
land across Saudi Arabia which means
Saudi Arabia will have to construct
Railway and Road lines which is very
feasible I mean there are some
engineering challenges in the Saudi
Arabian desert but it's certainly
something that can be done so it
continues within Saudi Arabia and then
it crosses over into Jordan from Jordan
into Israel the part of haa that uh the
adani group owns or controls there is
that and from Israel so from Saudi
Arabia through Jordan into Israel and
from Israel to Cyprus and
Greece Cyprus may or may not be there
but Greece will definitely be there the
port city of Paras where is the port of
peras do we need to
okay the port of pus is somewhere here
in
Greece
um somewhere
here but okay it doesn't matter let's
let's not waste time zooming into the
map but from India into the UA from UA V
Saudi Arabia Via Jordan into Israel and
from Israel by passing turkey you go to
Greece and probably to Rome Etc and
there could be some points um some
Transit points in North Africa as well
and what this does is that it it gives
the US and India an option that is an
addition to the option that we have in
Su the Su Canal the SW Canal is a very
important choke point and it it in
involves another choke point in the bab
Al Mand straight over here north of
jibu and there's been this issue with
the with the houis targeting shipping
through this region so if we do this
then we will have an alternative to the
Su Canal so it's great for India it's
great for the nations of the of the West
Asia region it's great for Europe it's
great for the US so so this plan was
announced during the uh G20 Summit in
Delhi in
2023 and just after this was announced
the the the terrorist attack on Israel
happened October 7 the Hamas terrorist
attack and that completely scuttled the
project the Saudis wanted this project
to start operations within a week or two
after it was signed but it's now been
more than a year so that's what imch is
and that's why it's important now what
happens now the question is Will trump
make it happen um look Hamas has been
thoroughly blasted and battered and uh
their leadership has been wiped out to a
large
extent uh so if the Israelis are able to
for want of a better term pacify Gaza
and the West Bank properly and there's
no more of of any conflict in the region
especially Gaza in the Middle East in
the West Bank then imch could could go
ahead it could certainly go ahead it
remains to be seen what the situation
with Iran is and how it evolves this
year because that's another un
unresolved
issue the Iran Israel
hostility and the back back and forth
missile and other attacks that happened
last year so if if the situation remains
peaceful IMC could certainly go ahead
this year and it it would be good for
the economy of India for the economies
of Europe and of course the nations in
the West Asia region uh the UAE Saudi
Arabia Jordan and Israel as well so it
would be great if this project goes
ahead this year it depends on whether
the Israelis are able to properly ensure
peace in their
region and whether there is any
hostility that continues between Israel
and Iran and if the US gets involved
then it's all it's going to destabilize
the region all over again so it depends
on all these
factors Vishal Kumar says recently lots
of articles are coming on the link
between Indus between the indust script
and Hindu culture but on the the
parallel there's an attempt to link the
script with dadian Origins as the chief
minister of Tamil Nadu has approved a
fund for the disa forment of the indos
script and we have found giraffes in
South India with matches the synu gati
sabata what do you think about that
okay so the prime so the so the chief
minister of Tamil Nadu has announced
a a prize for the decipherment of the
Indus Valley or harapan or sarasti suus
script yeah whether it's Prize or a fund
I'm not sure but it's a prize I think
right now the fact is that the script
has been
deciphered the script has been
deciphered it has been deciphered by
gentleman called
yajan Mr batra he has deciphered it and
soon you will be able to read the Indus
script like you read Hindi K Gaga all
that stuff with the Indus script
symbols so it's done now they can keep
on trying to Red decipher it into and
claim it this or that or whatever but
what yaj has has discovered is that it
is
sanskrit and uh announcement coming up
soon this comes up soon this this right
that is the gentleman G Mr batra who
deciphered the script so I have recorded
a podcast with him in which we go into
the whole detail we go into the
decipherment in great detail and it's
coming up next week so please look
forward to it it comes up next week and
the script is deciphered so let people
put up prizes and whatever and funds for
decipherment but it is done it is done
and it is done
conclusively so the sarasti Hindu script
was Sanskrit I mean it it encoded the
Sanskrit language it can encode any
language any script can encode any
language but the language it encoded was
Sanskrit that's done now you know the
acceptance of a disa forment can take
time it can take years it can take
decades but if the disa forment is
correct at the end of the day you're
going to have to agree with it
and this decipherment is correct so the
script is deciphered and the podcast
comes out next week and you can listen
to it and understand how it was
done prakar Gupta says many historians
claim that that ancient Indian
mathematics and astronomy were the
result of the introduction of Greek
influence after Alexander and the indog
Greek era so before Alexander there was
no mathematics and astronomy in India
right because many of the Great
mathematician and mathematicians and
historians like Arya butat and Brahma
gupt lived after the indog Greek era
what are the facts okay brahmagupta
lived in the 6th Century
ad uh arabat is said to have lived
somewhere in the first half of the first
Millennium ad and so on but um and so on
now let's understand some chronology Al
Alexander comes to India about 320
something BC right 327 or something BC
before that was there no scientific
technological advancement in India where
we living in in straw and grass Huts
where we living were we living on the
trees were we eating raw
meat we did we have no civilization in
India before
Alexander is that the
case we
had the sarasti Hindu phase of Indian
civilization of Indian
history so
let's let's look at it chronologically
if we look at Greece the oldest
historical era of Greece was Myan Greece
which is about 1750 BC to about 1,000 BC
Myan Greece but that's not the classical
ancient Greece the classical ancient
Greece is about 1,000 BC to about 1 AD
or until the Roman conquest of of Greece
which is before 1 AD which is a few
years years before 180 it was done by
Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony so they
conquer Greece and after that Greece is
permanently
subjugated so ancient Greece was roughly
1,000 BC to whenever Julius Caesar
conquered Greece and before ancient
Greece you had another period which was
meinian Greece which was 1750 BC to
1,000 BC Now Greek mathematics and
whatever science Etc that's in ancient
in the ancient Greek Greece period which
is about 1000 BC to about let's say
about 50 BC that's when all of that
happened the city stay and so-called
democracy and the pipian war and
technological advances the hotlights the
Cavalry um and whatever Science and
Mathematics and astronomy the Greeks
came up with all of that is about is
from 1,000 BC to about 50 BC okay when
it comes to Indian history the Saraswati
Hindu civilization phase of Indian
history the oldest sarasti snu
settlement that we have found thus far
is birana in harana up which goes back
to 7,500 BC it's about 10,000 years
before today compare that with 1750 BC
of
Greece now the early har so-called early
harapan phase is about 3,500 BC and the
mature harapan phase is 2600 BC during
the mature harapan phase 2600 BC or
thereabouts you have tremendous
technological advancements in
India it is a fully urbanized
civilization you have
standardization of map of of of weights
and measures your multi- stoed buildings
you have enormous
Harbors the harbors at Lal and and Dava
one of these Two
Harbors is larger than the modern Harbor
at vishakapatnam where the Indian
aircraft carriers can be accommodated so
the harapan our harapan era ancestors
built Harbors that could accommodate
today's aircraft
carriers you had tremendous Feats of
Hydro Engineering and whatnot do you
think you can have these accomplishments
without a knowledge of science
technology mathematics Etc and all of
this is way before Greece was even
dreamt of in somebody's
mind so if you look at the facts on the
ground it completely contradicts these
claims by whatever historians that
Indian mathematics and astronomy were
the result of the introduction of all
this from by the Greeks what utter
nonsense the Greeks were Primitives
compared to India I mean no resp
disrespect to our Greek friends but
India predates Greeks by thousands of
years by at least 5,000 years that's
just a fact right so yeah brahmagupta
lived recently AR but lived recently you
know in the context of the entirety of
Indian history these guys lived recently
it's like day before yesterday but
that's how old indan history is so if
you just look at the facts the fact that
we have such an incredibly
technologically advanced phase of Indian
history about 3,000 4,000 BC way before
Greece it tells you that we obviously
had tremendous advancements in
Mathematics and Technology and astronomy
okay Mathematics and Technology long
before Greece when it comes to astronomy
we have been recording astronomical
events for thousands of years uh where
is that uh let me Google that and put it
up
okay super
noova um
Kashmir okay so let's put this up on the
on the
screen our ancestors have been recording
celestial events astronomical events for
thousands of years so um here's this
article by the guardian let's see the
guardian article two Sons no it's a
supernova drawn two 6,000 years ago say
scientists so this Stone carving from
kashmir's bah Hama site was thought to
De to depict a hunting scene for decades
but now Indian researchers have
discovered that these that this is the
oldest depiction of a Dying star there
are see essentially two sons in the
carving and there's a hunter and there's
a deer and there's a dog and so on and
these this actually represents a sky
chart a chart with constellations and
the location of the sun and the location
of a star that exploded and if you go if
you if you use astronomical software and
you try to to find when was the last
time a supernova happened in this region
you have to go back about 6,000 years
before today it's Supernova hb9 that
exploded about 4,600 BC so we have been
recording astronomical
events from 4,600 BC thousands and
thousands of years six 7 thousand years
our
calendar so when the Greeks came to
India the Greek uh the Greek Ambassador
meganes who was who was based in patut
the morian court he said that the
Indians have this calendar called the
saari calendar that dates back to 6,000
something years before uh before today
so if you have a calendar that goes back
6 7,000 years calendars are based on
observations of cycles of solar lunar
and astronomical
cycles and he had a calendar that day
that went back six 7,000 years so to
claim that we had no understanding of
astronomy we we you cannot have a
calendar uh even a rudimentary calendar
without a decent understanding of
astronomy and we had a great
calendar so all these claims when you
look at them factually they evaporate
into nothingness
musco white says could you consider
recording a coherent series of V videos
about Indian history from the very
beginning up to the present day since
it's a huge and complicated topic it's
hard to find a reliable source not of
colonial origin or without Colonial
influence with a decent vision and
approach you have or at least you can
recommend some books uh but series of a
series of videos is still needed anyway
because most people don't read books I
know I'm sure it'll be very useful not
only for amicable interested Outsiders
like me but for fellow Indians as well
greetings from Mother Russia okay I've
just found out you have a course do you
have any plans to continue and make it
open for the wider audience in YouTube
and could you add a crypto payment
option in usdt for example well first of
all greetings to our friend from Moscow
um look I am currently doing a series on
US History it's just begun it's a long
journey uh if I were to do a series of
videos on Indian history put them out
once a week or so that would be an even
longer journey and it would be a very
very very large undertaking to do it
properly in detail it would involve a
lot of reading a lot of research a lot
of outlining and so on it's certainly
something I could do but it's not
something I can do right away it will
take me some time before I it'll be some
time before I can undertake such a
project but it's certainly a very
worthwhile project and I'm really really
glad that people from outside India
especially our friends from Russia are
interested in
this um I could try and see whether I
could add a crypto payment option usdd
Etc on the course that's what I could do
right away but uh thank you for the
suggestion it's something I would really
love to do in the future but it won't
happen right away because right now I am
busy in other projects but yeah
eventually it should happen me or
somebody else or whoever maybe me once
this this current project is over I I
could probably take this up so thank you
for the suggestion thank you very much I
really appreciate it and thank you for
your uh viewership really really
appreciate best
wishes sanjie says the US is using
Pakistan against India and on the other
side why is the US supporting the Afghan
Taliban who who are destabilizing
Pakistan does the US have any future
plan to use Taliban against India
okay interesting question look
okay we know the US has a historically
used Pakistan to destabilize India to to
counterbalance India the Americans in
the 1970s ' 80s 90s 2000s funded and
financed Pakistani terrorism against
India the pakistanis were doing it but
it was funded by the Americans we know
that the Kashmir Hindu Exodus all of
that was funded and financed and maybe
masterminded by the Americans
at least funded and
financed um so yes so Pakistan is their
attack dog against India has
historically been that way now India is
too big for that to be effective but it
still is a destabilizing factor Pakistan
and it's a us wasal we know that right
ever since Imran Khan was Ed and whoever
came to power it's a us wasal now it has
also emerged of late I mean earlier I
was the only person saying it but now
even Elon Musk has pointed fingers in
that direction and it's now known that
the Americans have been funding the
Taliban it's now conclusively
demonstrated I've been saying this since
2021 so uh the Americans are paying the
Taliban between 50 to 70 to maybe
hundred million doar in cash every week
lot of money right so why are the
Americans supporting the
Taliban who are anti- Pakistan because
Pakistan is supported by the US right
why do that
it's it's a very interesting
geopolitical
game they will use Pakistan to
counterbalance India but just to make
sure that the Pakistan is don't really
become too overconfident they will use
Afghanistan as a counterbalance to
Pakistan so full balance and Afghanistan
being on the US payroll also has the
effect of cutting off the Chinese belt
and Road initiative which was hopefully
supposed to go through Afghanistan and
it's not happening so the Chinese want
to invest in Afghanistan they want to
exploit Afghanistan's natural resources
mineral resources Copper from the mesak
region and whatnot but it's not
happening nothing is happening
impossible to do the Taliban is making
it impossible for the Chinese to do
anything the Chinese would have loved to
have the belt belt and Road
OB infrastructure project go via
Afghanistan westwards but that has also
not happened so
by supporting the Afghan Taliban the
Americans are ensuring that they are
essentially killing two birds with one
stone they are blocking the Chinese belt
and Road initiative they're blocking
Chinese access to Afghanistan that's one
bird second bird is Pakistan they are
keeping
Pakistan under a tight leash or at least
a loses loses leash so the Taliban can
can be activated any time the Pakistan
has become more
confident so yeah that's the game that's
being played does the US have any future
plan to use Taliban against India I
don't think so I don't think the Taliban
will be amable to fighting against India
the Taliban are pashon nationalists all
they want is to be left alone leave us
alone leave us alone to govern our
nation we'll do we will impose Sharia
we'll do whatever we want leave us alone
that's all they want they have no enmity
with India they have enmity with
Pakistan because Pakistan squats on
Taliban on Afghan territory the kar
pakun region is pashon majority from a
population perspective and the pashun
they want to reunify with with
Afghanistan so it's a huge territorial
dispute it's a long standing territorial
dispute and the Taliban wants that
territory back from Pakistan so Taliban
Pakistan bad relations they are
adversaries From taliban's perspective
they have nothing against India they
have no love for India let's understand
that they have no love for India but
they don't have any enmity towards India
either India has done a tremendous
amount of great work in Afghanistan the
past several decades so many infrastr
projects agriculture projects that have
that have helped the common man woman
and child India has not spent money
filling lining the pockets of corrupt
politicians in Afghanistan India has
spent billions of
dollars creating infrastructure projects
and agriculture projects and these have
all benefited the common person
including every single Taliban members
family
members so the Taliban have no desire to
be hostile towards India they to
somewhere in their heart they have some
degree of warmth towards India but no
love for India so it's that sort of
situation so I don't think even even
even if the US wants they can use
Taliban against India if they want they
can use many of their other terrorist
outfits Al-Qaeda
Isis whatever other terrorist outfits
the Americans have created and funded
they can if they want to use terrorism
against India they can use those but the
Taliban probably w't work for the
US okay Vikram geopolitical asks two
questions my views on Hillary Clinton
and George Soros getting the medal of
freedom from Joe Biden and Elon Musk
condemns George Soros for funding Hamas
supporting Nos and said that the
latter's hatred of humanity includes
Israel what are my
thoughts so we are right now witnessing
a transition in US geopolitics a
transition
first of all I think we all understand
that there is some extra governmental
extra Democratic Power Center that
exists in the US and they have been the
guys who have been running the nation
the past four years because the past
four years you had one person who was
mentally not there Joe
Biden to two to elderly to function
normally and you had Kamala Harris who
doesn't have the IQ required to be a
vice president or a stand president so
neither the president or nor the vice
president were capable of leading
leading the nation but somebody was
running the nation so it becomes very
clear that the US doesn't need a
president there's somebody running the
nation at all times and that's obviously
the the so-called deep state or whatever
you want to call it so I think
it's it's it's completely perfectly
clear Beyond any doubt that this
situation does exist in the
US now
so the Deep State they essentially
control the US and they control all the
US vasal and they control more than half
the
world if it does exist it looks very
clear that it does exist and they
interfere in various Nations including
their allies including their enemies
they include they interfere in the
Affairs of every nation through various
proxies and one of these Proxes has been
Geor
Soros uh I'll will not go into his life
and the career and all that but he has
been a very destructive influence on
various economies he destroyed economies
of entire nations and he runs all these
so-called philanthropic uh organizations
and all that that interfere in the
internal affairs of Nations and he's in
his 90s now his son is essentially
taking over and it is in recognition of
a lifetime of service that he was given
this Honor by the Deep State through the
hands of Joe Biden and now that his job
is done and he's too old he's going to
be set aside and his son may be allowed
to run the show but I think the focus
will now be on other
things so they will never not entirely
dispense with the Soros gang but they
have new tools in the toolbox the Deep
State and so that's what we are seeing
we see this we are seeing this
transition right now so they're thanking
the Old Guard Hillary Clinton Geor Soros
thank you for a job well done thank you
for a lifetime of service now sit down
and if needed we'll call upon you but
right now you are kind of in cold
storage and now we have new toys and new
tools to fight
with so that's why you see the new tool
Elon Musk condemning George
Soros right so so that's what we are
witnessing look Elon Musk is the new
face of the deep State okay great guy he
has achieved so much very very smart
guy he probably could end up being more
powerful than the US
president even though he can't be the US
president of course if Trump annexes
Canada then neon musk will probably
become a natural born US citizen because
or or
or could be could perhaps be that way if
he's a Canadian Citizen and then he
became a US citizen there could be some
some pathway for him to become US
president but Trump has but but Elon
Musk has played a great game he's become
the most the richest man in the world
maybe the most powerful
man maybe after or before the US
president we don't know but yeah
and you cannot achieve that without
being completely 100% aligned with the
objectives and agenda of the deep
state so yeah that's how I see
it chinglen kba yum says I am from
Manipur and I have seen burmes cookie
burmes chin cookie roaming freely
planting poppy near Indian Army Camps
killing civilians at will Indian army
and Assam rifles paramilitary Force did
nothing to them what's your opinion on
this furthermore National media talks
about foreign Han and Manipur Etc in the
man foreign Han in the Manipur conflict
but I've never seen Chinese and US
troops here only I have instead I've
seen Indian forces staying together with
burmes cooki militants supplying weapons
and Logistics to them even signing
suspension of of operation s oo
agreement with the militants so who's
the foreign hand here what's going
on see the suspension of operations s oo
agreement was signed by Mr chamaram then
then home minister I think of the
congress party in 2008 but you know what
2008 was a long ago long time ago Mr
Modi has been prime minister of India
for the past 10 plus years so I think
it's it's now to there's no point now
blaming the congress party and previous
governments for what's happening in
Manipur you can't keep blaming
them so whatever is being said over here
I think
it's impossible to refute
so I think you
know the Prime Minister has to answer
these
questions I can't answer these questions
well the Prime Minister has
uh has decided to observe a Val of
Silence when it comes to
Manipur so I think you know what can I
say either the prime minister or the
home minister one of them is the right
person to answer these questions very
factual
questions that's all I can say speak up
gentlemen Vikram Ador says as more and
more Nations develop Hypersonic missiles
how long will defense systems like S400
Patriot Etc be relevant considering the
fact that these missiles are faster than
sound and can't be intercepted by these
systems is there any system in the R&D
stage in the US Russia China Etc which
can neutralize these weapons in the
future see here's the
game from an offensive perspective I
want to have the fastest and deadliest
missile
possible from a defensive pers
perspective I want to have a system that
can intercept my deadliest missile the
game is always to be one step ahead of
the other either from a defense
perspective or from an offense
perspective from an offense perspective
you want to be one step ahead of the
Defenders so if the best system in the
world can can neutralize or or or or uh
intercept Mac 2 missiles then I want to
be at Mac 3 or Mac 5
if the best defense system missiles
defense system is capable of of of
intercepting Mac 5 missiles they then I
want to be at Mac 6 or Mac 7 or Mac 8
n or from a defensive perspective if the
best and fastest missile in the world is
Mac 9 then my I want to develop a system
that can neutralize and identify and
intercept neutralize Max 10 missiles so
the game is to be one step ahead of the
other
so right now many nations are developing
hypersonics India is in the game China
is in the game Russia is Russia has the
best Hypersonic missiles the Iranians
have Hypersonic missiles um the
Americans are obviously developing these
things so I think in this current
climate the S400 is pretty much going to
be obsolete when it comes to going two
to2 with the best missiles
systems so when it comes to the kinjal
the kinal is is is is
a cruise missile the siron is a
ballistic missile if I'm not mistaken
and there's others so there's a ton
there's the kinal the kinal is launched
from aircraft the siron may be a cruise
missile ballistic but it has like Mark 9
the siron and so on it it may even be
Mark 10 so when it comes to the siron
for example which let's say it's Mark 9
it can take out any aircraft carrier in
the world the UK's aircraft carriers are
already obsolete the two new ones are
already
obsolete so if the if the ciron missile
is launched towards a Target and the
target has an S400 the S400 is helpless
that's a
guarantee so obviously when it comes to
the best missile systems right now the
S400 will want will not be able to do
much against them the S4 can take care
of the majority of missile threats
ballistic not ballistic but cruise
missile threats and aircraft and all
that but when it comes to The Cutting
Edge the S400 will
fail uh the Russians have an S500 system
that's already being deployed which
probably will be much better than the
S400 it can even take out ballistic
missiles you know medium range of
whatever ballistic
missiles and soon they will need a S600
so you always have to keep improving
your capabilities keep augmenting your
capabilities just because you have the
S400 which is the best in the world
doesn't mean you can sit down and relax
you have to always keep the moment this
system is operational you to think about
how do I make it better and how do I
take it to a whole new level which is
the
S500 so it's going to always be that
game the missile developers will try and
their job is to make better and better
missiles I have a mark 9 missile now I
want to aim for Mark 11 you start the
the R&D process all over again better
materials better fuels better heat
signatures and
whatnot and so on so that's the game
it's a never- Ending game Predator
versus
prey um so U see if if there exist any
systems that can neutralize such threats
those systems will be extremely secret
highly classified so we will not know
about them even if they
exist Sara says will India take
will India take the Muslims or in po
inside India if India reclaims po if yes
it will affect Indian demography
internal security Hindu taxpayer money
will be spent on PO
Muslims you know every single askit's
episode I have multiple questions on
P now look if you want to take
Pok what will you do with the millions
of people who live in po obviously you
have to take them
right otherwise don't take po don't
reclaim po you can't evict millions of
people out of the place they've been
living in for for for decades for
Generations you can't will it in affect
India's demography internal security it
will definitely change India's
demographics to a certain extent it it
may definitely affect India's internal
security taxpayer money will be spent on
them yeah but then the question you to
ask yourself
is is India is is is this Hindu taxpayer
money most of it is okay but is India a
Hindu Nation India is not a Hindu Nation
by the way India is a secular socialist
republic right and in India Hindus are
essentially second class citizens aren't
they so what what what would it change
more of the same but at least you will
have P right
Vikram geopolitical says the Portuguese
and Spanish the Portuguese and Spanish
were much more chilled out than British
and French when it comes to colonialism
the indigenous tribes were not wiped out
in South America unlike North America
neither the Portuguese and Spanish
sucked out the resources of their
colonies unlike what France did in
Africa and Britain did in South Asia in
today's world the past Spanish and
Portuguese colonies have higher HDI and
GDP per capita y so
okay let's go to our friend Google and
and Google a few things to see whether
these claims out down here are correct
or
not so we open a fresh blank page of
Google and let me Google
Tierra
fuo Tierra del Fuego is an AR
archipelago in South America okay if I
go to the
map then it will show me what place okay
this region okay the southern tip of the
of South America now let's go back and
say
natives
natives the fuegians are the natives
okay what did they look
like so they looked like this let's
let's let's go back to Google and look
at
Wikipedia Wikipedia is a bad source of
information for India but in this case
it in many cases it's it's a bad source
of information but I'm just looking at
it
for the sake of convenience so the fans
fans are not are they were the
indigenous inhabitants of this place the
Fuego at the southern tip of South
America they have been wiped out of
existence these are Julius poer a person
who is killing various um these these U
natives shooting them like they're wild
animals check it out okay this is what
they looked like in 1915 they still
existed in 1915 look at these
innocent faces these children women men
children families
okay
uh so one of these uh cultures was
called the sik the
snam and yeah they were genocided as you
can see there was an internment camp and
all that and once again
killings these are children from 19 from
I wonder what happened to these two kids
and so on so this is just one example TI
fuo when it comes to the nation of
Argentina where are the natives when it
comes
to many parts of South America the
natives have disappeared they have been
entirely exter exterminated out of
existence if you read the accounts of
the Spanish conquistadors
who first um invaded various South
American
uh
cultures you will see that they were
anything but chilled
out they were brutal they were barbaric
they were
bloodthirsty whether it is uh herand
Cortez Franchesco
pizzaro
um
Coronado or delot or what whoever they
were
brutes they killed incredibly shocking
amounts of
people uh so I would very much disagree
that the Portuguese and Spanish were
much more chilled out than the British
and French what I would the truth is
that the British were much more
systematic and rigorous in Exterminating
native
populations the Portuguese and Spanish
did not do a thorough enough job the
Spanish did kill off many populations
like the the people I just show showed
you just now in the fuo also the arak
people of Hispanola and so many more but
if you look at North America if you look
at Florida if you look at many of these
places huge regions of the United States
and North America the natives have been
entirely
exterminated so the British did a much
better job of Exterminating the natives
the British eventually morphed into the
Americans I mean the United
States
uh when it comes to sucking out
resources the Spanish sucked out
everything of
value from the Inca from the Aztec from
various other places everything was of
value every single microgram of gold was
sucked out and sent to Europe to Spain
and it funded the Spanish the lavish
lifestyle of the Spanish code and the
various they were fighting in Europe
they sucked everything out the
Portuguese did not go to the Americas
they went eastwards and they did the
same thing wherever they would wherever
they could they were also bloodthirsty
and barbaric and brutal and they also
attempted to genocide everything out of
existence the Portuguese probably
weren't that good enough of course they
did unleash the Inquisition the brutal
barbaric
inhuman Inquisition on on Goa and so on
and they did a lot of bad things as well
in other places the the the the
Portuguese but overall when it comes to
being brutally effective the British
were far better a nation of bookkeepers
right shopkeepers whatever they were
very effective much more than the
Spanish and the
Portuguese uh the French were reasonably
good as well yes uh so today's past
Spanish and Portuguese colonies do they
have higher human development in index
HDI Argentina how is it former Spanish
colony not so good
Peru uh if you look at the whole map of
South America most of these are former
Spanish and Spanish colonies except for
Brazil which which has Portuguese
influence so if you look at these past
Spanish colonies the HDI and all is is
quite bad actually if you look at the
Dominican Republic where the capitalist
Santo Domingo City that Columbus founded
abysmal levels of of everything terrible
economy tremend corruption rampant
corruption and so on when it comes to
the British colonies in the in the
Americas all are first world when it
comes to the Spanish colonies they're
all second or third
world in Asia it's a different story but
we're talking about the Americas here so
yeah so I don't think you have to really
study history in more detail to
understand that the Spanish and the
Portuguese were not chilled out they
were just as brutal and barbaric as any
other European Invader of other of of
non-european
cultures Shankar Kar says do you think
if Germany had respected the molotov
ribben trop pact and not invaded the
USSR and had fully focused on uring
England Falls then they would have had
significant chances of winning the
second world war after in England went
down after England down the entire
Western Front was secur C probably then
Focus okay all right so the question
is okay the molotov reent the molotov
renthop pact was an agreement
between the US USSR and Germany Molotov
USSR ribbon trop Germany okay this
was an agreement with secret Clauses so
it was a non-aggression pact that we
won't attack each other we won't be
aggressive to each other and there was a
secret there were a bunch of secret
Clauses in which it they decided on how
to divide up pooland and Eastern
Europe so that was the PCT it was signed
in 1939 if I am not mistaken in the very
very beginnings of the second world war
and this pact was unilaterally broken by
Adolf Hitler in 1941 when he launched
operation Barbarosa which was an
invasion of the USSR
by this
time the Germans had taken over the
entirety of Europe
barring the
UK they' taken over France they taken
over everything else the USSR was free
was was was still independent on the
East and in Western Europe there was
only one independent entity the UK and
there was this whole Battle of Britain
that happened and all and so on and then
Hitler decides to invade the USSR
and he was his forces were almost on the
outskirts of Moscow they could see mosow
from Moscow from binoculars but then he
made a fatal mistake Hitler and he
decided to prioritize the March the The
Invasion down south towards the Caspian
SE where you have lots of oil and gas
supplies resources because that would
that was something that Germany needed
but he did not prioritized the push
towards Moscow he prioritized the push
towards the South the Caucasus region
and he got up in Leningrad the Battle of
Leningrad and all that was which was a
complete disaster and once you make a
mistake in Russia something really bad
happens and that something really bad is
old man
winter and once winter sets in you are
doomed if you're an if you're an
invading Force Napoleon learned
it and it destroyed him and the same
thing happened to the Germans so there
were the outskirts of Moscow when they
started
freezing like just freezing to
death
um and even if let's say they had not
prioritized the Caucasus and had gone
just straight for Moscow even then there
was no guarantee of winning because the
USSR was has inexhaustible territory you
know Napoleon took Moscow he got nothing
out of it the the Russian government
simply moved out of Moscow and burned
the city and then handed over to
Napoleon it was a hollow Victory he
spent a month in a hollow burned out
shell of a city the the Russians would
have done the same thing had Hitler
decided to prioritize the march on
Moscow they would have burned Moscow and
Hitler would have taken an empty burned
out
City so I think overall it was a mistake
to attack the
USSR of course Hitler realized that the
USSR was enormously powerful it had
tremendous amounts of resources so
that's why he wanted probably to launch
a decapitation decapitation strike on
Salin take out Salin take out the
leadership of the CC of the of the uh of
the Communist party and then you can do
a regime change and then it's fine but
he miscalculated by prioritizing the
Caucasus instead of Moscow in that case
but what that did is that it gave the
Americans and the British time to you
know some breathing space the Americans
were able to resupply the UK and then
eventually they were able to mark on
Normandy do the crossing of the of the
of the English Channel land in Normandy
and start taking over Peace by pece
France and things go bad around
Barbarosa around the time that they the
the Germans mess up in Barbarosa the
winter of 41 the spring of 42 that's
when the tide turns and uh the credit
for the victory is given to the
Americans but it was the Soviets who did
who did the vast majority of the
fighting and the dying and the
winning yeah but it was a mistake
Mistake by Hitler I think at the end of
the day I think he wanted to win
everything he wanted to conquer the
whole world the same kind of huis that
Napoleon
had uh he had already conquered much of
Europe had he just settled down and
Consolidated his his his power in Europe
instead of attacking the
USSR even if UK the UK remained
independent he would have had a much
better outcome for for his country
possibly yeah so it's a lot of ifs and
buts but that's how things
went G of J mumi says how could France
how did France manage to remain quasi
independent with a quazi independent
foreign policy self control over its
nukes and most significant geopolitical
player in Europe after the US on the
other hand Britain which had the biggest
empire and was once the most powerful
player it was a super
power um couldn't manage to have all of
the above what did the French do
differently from the
British yeah good question good question
so what did the French what do the
French have that the other members of
NATO don't have is a good question it's
a good way to look at
it there's one thing the French don't
have that everybody else has the French
don't have us occupation forces on their
territory there's not a single American
military base on French soil there's no
permanent
US
troops stationed anywhere in
France France is a me member of NATO and
there are some obligations but there is
not a single American Military base or
troop presence on French soil that's
what they did
differently Every Other Nation Germany
Germany has permanent US military basis
it's under US military occupation the
same goes with with Italy the same is
the case for many other n members of
NATO and the European Union turkey even
Harbors American nuclear nuclear
missiles on its soil the Netherlands
also
apparently and when it comes to the UK
they also have a significant US military
presence on UK
territory so that's what France did
differently now the UK until the 1980s
was very
independent um until as long as Margaret
Thatcher was in power and there was a
transition period when John Major was in
power when the UK was still kind of
independent and everything
collapsed the sovereignty collapsed once
uh Tony Blair came to power uh he is um
referred to
as as George W Bush's
poodle very unkind thing to say but
maybe it's factual
so as long as Margaret tacha was in
power the UK had a very strongly
independent foreign
policy they went against us wishes when
they invaded the Faulkland the the
malvas war the fand's war 81 was it and
so on and you may remember there was
something called the troubles in Ireland
so the British uh they occupy Northern
Ireland so Northern Ireland is British
occupied Northern Ireland okay like we
have Pakistan occupied Kashmir similarly
we have British occupied Northern
Ireland it's not British or English
territory but they occupy it and there
was this long
Insurgency that tore the country for
decades the Insurgency was Irish
nationalists and Patriots fighting the
occupation forces of the British and
there Bomb Blast and terrorist attacks
and freedom fight attacks and whatnot
for decades
bombings
shootings all kinds of British
atrocities against Irish people in
Ireland and so on and all of this went
on for decades and it's funny that the
moment Tony Blair comes to power and
becomes Pro
us immediately the Irish troubles
end and the good Sunday or whatever
agreement is signed and everything is
over how did that happen like that as if
by Magic the moment the UK becomes Pro
us and the proper vasal instantaneously
the Irish Insurgency ends how's that
happen how is it even
possible is there some somewhere two and
two that we can add
together maybe that is so that's how the
British were able to the the Americans
were able to take over the
British and they already controlled much
of Western Europe but France has always
managed to stay out of this by ensuring
that there is no US military presence on
French soil so that is what France has
done
differently feline lover says I know
this is not geopolitical history but
what do you think about the Asiatic lion
relocation program the problems that are
being faced because of the Gujarat
government refusing to share alliance
with other states this is bad for the
long-term well-being of the animal so we
have to understand that this animal was
once found throughout large parts of
India
not just in Gujarat but all across India
India is the
only part of the world where you have
Lions as well as Tigers but the British
policies ensure that the cheetah was
exterminated and the lion and tiger were
both persecuted and at the end of the
day the lion ended up existing only in
the gear Forest region of Gujarat a
small part of Gujarat and that's what
the situation is today in the past it
was it was present in Mesopotamia in
Persia and other parts of Asia it's the
Asian land even in Saudi
Arabia so it only exists in Gujarat
today in the gear region and it is good
for the well-being of the species that
it is distributed geographically across
various parts of India so that if there
is some kind of epidemic or some kind of
virus outbreak or something in one part
of India it doesn't kill the entire land
population and then we are done it's
over
right so it makes sense for
this species to be distributed across
various habitats in in multiple parts of
India and that's why there is this
Asiatic lion relocation project and they
have proposed various places madhya
Pradesh and some other locations but
unfortunately the government of Gujarat
is is blocking this move because this is
this lion is the pride of Gujarat we are
the only state of India that has a lion
and we will not give it up we will not
share it with with other States because
that will reduce the importance of
Gujarat I think that is a very myopic
way of looking at the world okay the
species is is is a National
Treasure we don't want the species to
die out it just takes one virus outbreak
or or disease outbreak to kill an entire
population it is very important that
we um we we distribute the species
across various parts of India so I think
it would be
um a good move for the Gujarat
government to allow this project to go
ahead
right I hope it
happens okay photo here Patel says why
are life forms so fragile why did most
of them evolve mechanisms of
reproduction than of repairing
themselves for eternity I think it will
certainly be possible to be immortal in
the future if we keep on having
breakthroughs in the in science so why
didn't nature make us
Immortal look I don't know why nature
did not make us Immortal uh there are
certain species of jellyfish that are
apparently Immortal but organisms like
us uh we are
not now are we that
fragile see let's take a phone okay a
phone I slam the phone on on on on on
the floor or a table it will
shatter I take my hand and I slam
it perfectly fine same amount of force
so life forms aren't
fragile life forms are anti
fragile okay you can you can deadlift or
squat 200 kilos if you train yourself
well enough and you can take the entire
weight on your shoulders if you're
squatting if you're pulling the deadlift
movement then then 200 kilos on eight
fingers that's all that's it that's how
you're pulling it of course if you're if
you do it properly you will not hold it
in your fingers but in in the palm of
your hand but you can imagine how much
pressure is being exerted on on this
soft tissue and yet you thrive so we are
not fragile we are actually antifragile
we can survive a lot we can survive a
whole lot but yes we have a limited
lifespan it depends on the length of the
Tome and as your
Tome they shorten you show signs of
aging and eventually you no longer can
stay alive at some point in life but
hopefully by the time you pass on your
genes and your future Generations can
Thrive and that's the way it is so I
don't know why it has evolved this way
or that way maybe there was a good
evolutionary reason for it to be this
this way um but we are not that fragile
we are actually quite robust we can take
a lot
uh I'm not sure if it will be possible
to be immortal in the future I'm not
sure if it's even desirable to be
immortal in the future let me tell you
why
look we typically live 80 90 70 to 100
years 100 is like an outlier typically
70s and 80s if you live until that age
you've lived a good life and a long life
now you will see that most people most
people who live to that age start having
issues with their memory right some of
them some people are are super sharp
even in their hundreds even past 100
years of age but most people by the age
of 70 80 90 they start having issues
with their
memory so the and and most people
believe that we only use 5% of our brain
capacity which is an absolute myth we
use the fullest of our brain capacity
most of us we use it
entirely now our brain has these neural
connections synapses and all that and it
is these neural connections and all of
that that creates that that that is the
mechanism of the storage of memories in
the brain and let's say your brain can
have can will be full of memory by the
time it's by the time you're 80 or 90
years old now let's say we develop the
means of of extending this human body's
lifespan to 200
years okay let's say let's say we can
hypothetically do it in the future
what's going to happen to your brain and
the memories it stores eventually your
brain is going to run out of space for
storing
memories and you're going to have to
start overwriting new memories of new
experiences over the old memories which
means by the time you're 150 you have
you may have forgotten the first 50
years of your
life and you may no longer be the same
person and of course is is the brain
ages you may you may prolong the life of
the body but what about the life of the
brain the brain May develop defects like
like the plaques that are typical of
Alzheimer's disease and whatnot what
will you do about that so you may
prolong the life of the body but end up
with a completely damaged mind
do you want
that maybe it's an experience that's
that's torturous for the one who is
experien experiencing that maybe it's
not desirable maybe there's a reason why
we live a certain amount of years so I
don't know at the end of the day I'm
speculating here but think along these
lines try and think outside of the
box okay it's not just a physical thing
being Immortal you have to be immortal
and and have sufficient conscious and
sufficient quality of life and if
immortality gives you mental torture do
you want that if it if it ends up
meaning that you are no longer the
person you were when you were born then
do you want
that to what what's the point of that do
you really want to be immortal that's a
question right
then
okay okay two questions by one by Sun
Moon and the other by vicam geopolitical
is 90 hours working per week will it
make India great again this is not
healthy at any cost lnt boss SN
subramanium endorses 90 hour work week
has he gone mad do you think India
should also have Labor friendly laws
like
Europe okay and Naran morti also has
said that we need to work like 300 hours
a week or something right so here's the
deal if you are working 80 hours a day
and seven
days if you 9 90 hours 90 hours per week
and you have 7 days in a week so that's
more than 12 hours a day 12 7 are 84
it's almost 13 hours a day let's say you
take one day off then it's like 90 hours
in a in in six days it's 15 hours a
day so a person who is asking you to
work that long first of all is he going
to ensure that everybody's paid
sufficiently and secondly if you're
working 15 hours a day
will you not go
mad will you see there are some there
are certain examples you know that one
can put
forth I can think of two Nations that
have a similar work ethic one is South
Korea one is
Japan this this focus on productivity
this this focus on working tremendously
hard extremely brutal brutally long work
hours and all that South Korea as well
as Japan look at Japan today look at
South Korea today jaan's demography is
collapsing their birth rates have
collapsed they could end out of they
could they could you know they could no
longer have children in the country by
2070 there may be nobody born in Japan
after 20170 that's the direction in
which Japan is going because of this
brutally brutal work culture and you can
see the same thing happening in South
Korea the birth rates have collapsed
nobody wants to have children anymore
so if you make people work that hard
they will they may be able to work that
hard but everything else will suffer
there'll be no family life there'll be
no children anymore the nation will
cease to exist as a population within
100 years maybe within 50
years so the South Korean thing started
in the 1960s and70s
that's about 50 60 years ago and see
where they are today by 2050 they could
be in an abysmal State of Affairs South
Korea so when you force people to work
that hard whether it's motivated or not
whether it's just by forcing them you're
going to end up collapsing the entire
demography of the
country and that will destroy the
country long
run and the second thing is can you even
motivate somebody to work that that hard
now you know it's like
this the the future of the nation
doesn't depend on the entire
population the future of the nation and
the civilization depends on the top
performers which is the
0.1% they set the standards and
everybody else tries to maintain some
semblance of that but it's the success
of the 0.1% that determines the future
of the country now what if you make the
0.1% work 15 hours a
day what is so India's population
is 1.5 billion oneth of that is 150
million 1/10th of that is 15
million and 1/10th of that is 1.5
million so let's say you make 1.5
million Indians which is 0.1% of 1.5
crores 1.5 million Indians they will be
made to work 90 or work weeks the
question is how will you motivate
them you know if the government is doing
its best to take India in the right
direction and if Society gives you
everything that you need in exchange for
working that hard then you'll be
motivated but when you have this
crumbling
infrastructure when you have the lack of
Merit when you have people who work hard
being taxed and others not paying any
tax when you have
inequality when you
have
uh an hinduphobic apath State when you
have all these
problems and when you have other nations
that do so well and and give so much
back to their people
how will you motivate people to work
that hard right so on the one hand you
expect people to work that hard on the
other hand you you expect them to ask
for nothing in return not better living
standards not better preferential
treatment not less taxes nothing no
recognition nothing then who will work
hard so I think working 90 hours per
week is madness even expecting most
people to do it voluntarily is madness
people work that hard only if they have
a very clear goal which is personal to
them and it's not forever maybe I have
to work 15
hours 90 hours a week for the next two
years but at the end of the day I get
this big jackpot which is going to be my
achievement in mine alone then yeah I
can sacrifice everything in work 90 or
weeks for two years but if you ask
people to just indefinitely keep working
90 or work weeks and they get nothing in
exchange in return for that it's not
going to happen
I would say let's have a 40-hour work
week but let's give let's
give employment to all 1.4 billion
Indians can we do that that itself is
enough to completely supercharge India's
growth even that's not happening right
now so that's a
problem Sun Moon says what are your
thoughts on
veganism veganism veganism is is where
uh so we have we know what vegetarianism
is we have lots of vegetarians in India
it's been a cultural practice for many
many Indians
historically vegetarianism is when you
don't eat any
meat so your main main diet is
vegetables and vegetable products plant
products and vegetarians also uh consume
dairy products which is milk and cheese
and paneer and all that that's
vegetarianism veganism means you cut out
all all animal products all dairy
products so you can't even consume milk
you can't even eat cheese or any such
thing you can have almond milk and
almond cheese and tofu and things like
that so that's an extreme extreme
variant of
vegetarianism what are my thoughts I
think it's up to you you want to be a
vegan be a vegan you want to be
vegetarian be a vegetarian it's up to
you entirely I think veganism is a
little too extreme the way I see it okay
it's up to you whatever you want to do
the vi SE is like that I think
uh but at the end of the day it's your
choice I think veganism may be overly
restrictive it may end up uh causing
health issues I think vegetarianism we
know is sustainable because Indians have
practiced that for thousands of years so
vegetarianism is sustainable you can be
healthy and live a good life as a
vegetarian as a vegan I'm not very sure
about that of course some people may
disagree but it's up to you
and at the end of the day it's your
choice and nobody can take that away
from
you akat says I want to start listening
to Indian classical music any good
places to start from well I could do a
2hour live stream on Indian classical
music so Indian classical music is the
world's oldest musical tradition it's an
incredibly profound and Rich musical
tradition the greatest mus musical
tradition the world has ever seen and
most Indians don't know about it so
that's why we get get this question and
I'm glad we get this question so when it
comes to Indian classical music you have
various instruments for for example you
have the flute you have the satar you
have you have the sarod you T and of
course you have vocal music which is
singing when it comes to Sitar so first
of
all if you want to listen to Indian
classical music you should go to YouTube
I think YouTube has plenty of material
for you to
uh to to to look at okay so when it
comes to Sitar players I would recommend
see three of the
greats one is Pandit Rish Shankar the
late Pandit Rish Shankar the other is
the late pundit nikil banery the third
is the late pundit vad Khan three of the
greats I'm sure there are many more but
I'll not name all of them so anything
that these three have produced is is
bound to be great not just good but
great when it comes to the flute you
have two of the greats panalal Goos and
Hari Prasad jasia their music is is
beautiful when it comes to the sod which
is a fretless string instrument you have
two of the greats
inad amjad Ali Khan and ustad Ali Akbar
Khan beautiful music there then you have
instruments like the shahai bismah Khan
was was was one of the greats of the
Shai the sanur which is a string
instrument that you hammer it with these
little little hammers sanur uh shiv
Kumar Sharma is one of the Great and the
great Pandit Bajan soori my God what a
great sandur player he was but very
obscure no one knows about him Pandit
bjan soori amazing amazing beautiful
music when it comes to vocal uh
classical music which is singing you
have the great Ms subal lakmi karnatic
music so in Indian classical music you
have two you have two categories which
is Northern Indian classical music and
the karnatic music which is Southern
Indian music
they have the same ragas and all with
different names so Ms subaki was one of
the great vocalists you have Pandit
beims and josi one of the great
vocalists also people like Pandit jash
uh kishori amonkar if you like the kayal
style then you have rajin sjin Mishra if
you like the drupad style of singing
which is one of the oldest
primordial forms of vocal singing then
you have the dagger
Brothers two generations of dagger
Brothers dagger dagger buhu they say uh
two generations of them and so on so
there's so much to peruse and then
there's also the you to understand what
a Raga is because Indian classical music
is Raga based Raga in in standard guitar
playing you have scales which is just
the Saran and up and down and you can
have other scales with with you know
other notes beyond the the major notes
you have minor notes flat notes and
augmented notes and uh sharp nodes and
so on so forth that various scales exist
okay mix solian scale and all that but a
Raga is more than a scale a raaga has an
ascending scale and a descending scale
it has a major note a dominant note and
a subdominant note it also has drone
notes and in a Raga up the ascending and
descending scales can be different so
there are many ragas that are that
depend on the time of the day you have
morning ragas afternoon ragas evening
ragas dusk ragas Dawn yagas night ragas
and all you also have seasonal ragas
like rainy season and all that so malhar
is a season is a rainy season Raga ragab
Vias ragab or Dawn
ragas raag J rag Mara or or Dusk ragas
and so on so much so much more and then
so there it's it's it's a whole system
so if you like happy ragas I would say
listen to
Raga Bahari very happy
it's a pentatonic Raga five notes and so
on so there's a lot to lot to say so
these are some of the recommend
recommendations I can give you check it
out and good luck on the journey I wish
more people would listen to Indian
classical music beautiful absolutely
beautiful okay we are almost at the end
of today's live stream geopolitical dub
gives a great recommendation L bimp
palri bimp palash Shri also called bimp
palas
yeah yeah indeed and sparkling Lotus so
sparkling Lotus says Raa Mal it's a
night Raga beautiful Raga and if you
listen to this to night Raga you
actually feel sleepy you know that so
malos was called malav koshik back in
the day now it's called
Mal yes
indeed okay let's take maybe a couple of
questions from the live chat Amisha asks
do worm holes exist we have never
seen a wormhole and and we have never
seen an object that we have been able to
confirm is a wormhole you know we we we
know of many black holes that exist the
first black hole that was discovered
ever was the signus 61 black hole uh and
now we know that there are black holes
all over the place there's one in our
own galaxy The Milky Way galaxy and uh
so we know of many black holes today but
it's also possible that many of these
black holes could possibly be the mouths
of wormholes you know it's possible
because wormholes mouth would also have
very similar characteristics as a
standard black hole so maybe they exist
maybe they just pretending to be black
holes you know maybe at the heart at the
center of every Galaxy there's a
wormhole not a black hole possible it's
possible but we don't know for sure so
there are no
confirmed uh there are no confirmations
of worm holes existing but we know
theoretically from the field equations
of of general relativity Wormhole
Solutions exist so wormholes should
exist
and what would a wormhole look like we
think of a wormhole as as a hole in a
sheet of paper right but a wormhole
exists in four-dimensional SpaceTime and
therefore if a hole in a sheet of paper
is
two-dimensional then a wormhole would
have three dimensions so a wormhole
would actually be spherical it would not
be a hole in SpaceTime it would be a
spherical object you go in there and you
you end up somewhere else that's what a
wormhole would look like but we don't
know we don't have any confirmations of
any bumbles thus
far okay
[Music]
okay anything else I know there's a
million questions
but I think I'm going to have to end it
here
now okay I'm going to end the the live
stream right here should I take one more
I guess not I guess it's already 2 hours
15 minutes so thank you so much for all
your questions apologies to all of you
whose questions I could not take to day
but we're going to keep doing this week
after week and hopefully I take
everybody's questions please ask your
best questions every time and I'll take
the best of the lot so keep asking
questions and keep raising your
standards and I will see you in the next
live stream reasonably soon enough next
week until then take care thank you and
I'll see you soon bye